<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


  <chapter id="language">
    <title>Language</title>

    <para>Consistent labelling creates a familiar environment that the user can navigate comfortably. The more familiar the environment, the easier task of finding information.</para>

    <sect1 id="labels">
      <title>Labels</title>
      
      <sect2 id="language-controls"> 
	<title>Controls</title> 
	<para>Clear, consistent and concise labelling of controls helps users to work out the purpose of a window or dialog they have never seen before. To a visually-impaired user, clear labels are even more important. A user who relies on a screenreader has no assistance from icons, layout, or spacing to work out what the controls do, so clear labelling is essential.</para>
	
	<para>Guidelines:</para>
	
	<itemizedlist> 
	  <listitem><para>Create short labels.  The reasons for keeping labels as short as possible are as follows:
	    <itemizedlist> 
		<listitem><para>Reduces the expansion of text when translated, and thus minimizes the effort required to localize the UI. Translated English text can expand up to 30% in some languages.</para></listitem> 
		
		<listitem><para>Facilitates the use of translation engines.</para></listitem> 
		<listitem><para>Improves speed of comprehension for the user.</para></listitem> 
	      </itemizedlist> 
         </para>
	    
	    <para> A word of caution, however: do not shorten your labels to the point of losing meaning. A three-word label that provides clear information is better than a one-word label that is ambiguous or vague. Try to find the fewest possible words to satisfactorily convey the meaning of your label.</para></listitem> 
	  
	  <listitem><para>Avoid functional descriptions.  As well as increasing the wordcount of the UI, descriptive labels can also conflict with information provided in documentation </para></listitem> 
	  
	  <listitem><para>Use standard terms.  You can find a list of standard user interface terms in the<emphasis> GNOME Documentation Style Guide, Recommended Terminology</emphasis>.</para></listitem> 
	  
	  <listitem><para>Apply UI capitalization rules.  See <xref linkend="layout-capitalization"/> for guidelines about capitalization of user interface labels </para></listitem> 
	</itemizedlist>

      </sect2> 
      
      <sect2> 
	<title>Tooltips</title> 
	
	<sect3>
	  <title>Toolbar Tooltips</title>
	  
	  <para>A toolbar tooltip is the short description of a toolbar control's functionality that the user sees when they mouse over it.</para>

	  <para>Guidelines:</para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist> 
	    <listitem><para>Concisely state the purpose of the control.  If the control directly duplicates a menu item, make the tooltip the same as the corresponding menu item.</para></listitem> 

	    <listitem><para>Use header capitalization rules. See <xref linkend="layout-capitalization"/>.</para></listitem> 
	  </itemizedlist>            
	  
	</sect3> 
	
	<sect3>
	  <title>Application Tooltips</title> 

	  <para>An application tooltip is the short description of your application that the user sees when they mouse over the launcher or menu item for your application.  It is stored in the <structfield>comment</structfield> field of your application's <filename>desktop</filename> file.</para>

	  <para>Guidelines:</para>
	  <itemizedlist> 
	    <listitem><para>Create short tooltips. Aim to accurately communicate the functionality of an element with the fewest words possible.</para></listitem> 
	    <listitem><para>Use sentence capitalization rules. See <xref linkend="layout-capitalization"/>.</para></listitem> 
	    
	    <listitem><para>Use standard punctuation rules, with the exception that you do not use a period to end the tooltip. </para></listitem> 
	    
	  </itemizedlist> 
	</sect3> 
      </sect2> 
      
      
      <sect2> 
	<title>Menus</title> 
	
	<para>Guidelines:</para>
	
	<itemizedlist> 
	
	  <listitem><para>Use the recommended standard labels for menu items and titles, where they exist. Do not use synonyms such as <guimenuitem>Exit</guimenuitem> instead of <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem>. See <xref linkend="standard-menus"/> for a list and descriptions of standard menu items and titles.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Use header capitalization rules for all menu items and titles. See <xref linkend="layout-capitalization"/>.</para></listitem> 
	    
	</itemizedlist> 
	
      </sect2>
      
    </sect1>

<!--
    <sect1 id="language-labels">
      <title>Labels</title>
      
      <sect2 id="language-text-labels">
	<title>Controls</title>
	<para>FIXME: Clear, consistent and concise labelling of controls is essential.  It helps users work out the purpose of a window they've never seen before, quickly find the information they want, and navigate around it easily.</para>

	<para>To a visually-impaired user, the labels you write are even more important.  A user relying on a screenreader will have no assistance from icons, layout, or spacing to work out what your controls do, so clear labelling is vital.</para>

	</sect2>
      
      <sect2 id="language-tooltips">
	<title>Tooltips</title>
	<para>FIXME</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="language-menus">
	<title>Menus</title>
	<para>FIXME</para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>

-->

    <sect1 id="language-errors">
      <title>Warning and Error Messages</title>
      <para>FIXME: Tell the user what the problem is, what they can do about it, and, if possible, offer to do it for them.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="language-help">
      <title>Online Help</title>
      <para>Refer to GNOME Documentation Styleguide</para>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>

