<chapter id="gtest" status="draft">
<title>Testing - GOK (GNOME Onscreen Keyboard)</title>
<para>
Your application should be usable via <application>gok</application>; key input should be generated entirely by <application>gok</application>, not the keyboard. The aim here would be to work with your application and the desktop in general, ensuring any type of character input can be performed with the on-screen keyboard.
</para>
<para>
The <application>gok</application> application ships with the GNOME Desktop so should already be present. For full documentation, refer to <ulink url="http://www.gok.ca">the official gok site</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
Follow these steps to verify the correct operation of <application>gok</application> with your application:
</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Login into the GNOME desktop
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Run <application>gok</application>
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Start your application
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Provide input to your application with a pointing device (e.g., mouse or head-tracker) and <application>gok</application>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Work using the auto-completion and word prediction features of <application>gok</application>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Verify that <application>gok</application> enables and disables the <guibutton>Menus</guibutton> and <guibutton>Toolbars</guibutton> buttons based on the kind of application invoked; for example, the <guibutton>Menus</guibutton> and <guibutton>Toolbars</guibutton> buttons are disabled for the 'Font properties' capplet, but the same buttons are enabled for the <application>Gedit</application> application.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Verify that the <application>gok</application> on-screen keyboard provided by the <guibutton>Compose</guibutton> button can be used to type in any text for the selected application; run <application>Gedit</application>, click on the text area, and then click on the <guibutton>Compose</guibutton> button in <application>gok</application>. Select the required keys from the on-screen keyboard. The characters should appear in the <application>Gedit</application> text area.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Verify that the <guibutton>Launcher</guibutton> button allows the user to launch any of the <application>Terminal</application>, <application>Web Browser</application> or <application>Text Editor</application> applications.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Verify that the <guibutton>Activate</guibutton> button allows the user to activate any of the currently running application windows on the user's desktop, including GNOME panels and the GNOME desktop.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Verify that the <guibutton>Menus</guibutton> button lists all the available menus in the current application. Verify that clicking on a menu button displays the sub-menu and menu items contained within the sub-menu. Finally, verify that clicking on a menu item activates the menu item. For example, click on the <application>Help Browser</application> application and click on the <guibutton>Menus</guibutton> button. The <application>GOK</application> window now displays the <guibutton>File</guibutton>, <guibutton>Go</guibutton> and <guibutton>Help</guibutton> buttons (the <application>Help Browser</application> menus). Click on the <guibutton>File</guibutton> button and it displays the <guibutton>New Window</guibutton> and <guibutton>Close Window</guibutton> buttons (menu items).
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Verify that the <guibutton>Toolbars</guibutton> button lists all the available buttons in the application toolbar. For example, click on the <application>Help Browser</application> application and then click on the <guibutton>Toolbars</guibutton> button. The <application>GOK</application> window now displays the <guibutton>Back</guibutton>, <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> and <guibutton>Home</guibutton> buttons.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Verify that the <guibutton>UI Grab</guibutton> button displays all the button objects for the selected application window. For example, open the 'Font Properties' capplet and click on the <guibutton>UI Grab</guibutton> button in the <application>GOK</application> window. The <application>GOK</application> window should now display the names of the buttons in the capplet - <guibutton>Sans</guibutton>, <guibutton>Sans-serif</guibutton>, <guibutton>Close</guibutton> and <guibutton>Help</guibutton>.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
</chapter>
